Catalog of the Walt Whitman Literary Manuscripts in The Yale Collection of American Literature, Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Published by The Walt Whitman Archive in collaboration with the University of Nebraska-Lincoln Libraries.
- Washington as a Central Winter Residence, 1871–1872; yal.00328; xxx.00862; prose 6 leaves handwritten (Folder 119)
  This manuscript touches on the developing "distinctive metropolitan American Character" of Washington, including the city's status as a literary center. Portions of this manuscript were used in Washington as a Central Winter Residence and Authors of Washington, the latter of which was published in two installments. The first installment appeared in the 6 January 1872 issue of the Washington Evening Star, which also included Washington as a Central Winter Residence. The second installment was published in the 9 January 1872 issue of the same. For more details regarding how this manuscript contributed to these two pieces of journalism, see Martin G. Murray, Two Pieces of Uncollected Whitman Journalism: 'Washington as a Central Winter Residence' and 'The Authors of Washington,' Walt Whitman Quarterly Review 20 (Winter/Spring 2003), 151-176.
- [Walt Whitman (from Holland and English], 1890–1891; yal.00335; xxx.00864; prose handwritten (Box 3, Folder 126)
  Draft of a biographical entry on Whitman that appeared nearly verbatim in G. Washington Moon's Men and Women of the Time: A Dictionary of Contemporaries (Routledge 1891).
- Putrid Politics, 1873–1875; yal.00342; xxx.00525; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 3, Folder 138)
  A draft fragment composed on two scraps of paper, pasted together to form one leaf. In this manuscript, Whitman addresses the symptoms and causes of the Civil War. The ideas presented in this manuscript appeared in Memoranda During the War ( 1875–76 ) before being revised and collected in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882 ) as Origins of Attempted Secession: Not the whole matter, but some side facts worth conning to-day and any day. On the verso of one scrap is a draft letter, addressed to A. R. Butts, dated 29 December 1873.
- O blare! blare!, 1850–1856; yal.00451; xxx.00865; prose poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 3, Folder 140)
  A scrap of paper featuring heavily revised poetic lines. The verso contains a prose fragment, the bulk of which is struck through. The connection between these fragments and Whitman's published work is unclear.
- In the gymnasium, 1850–1855; yal.00452; xxx.00048; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 3, Folder 140)
  Two poetic fragments, written on the front and back of one leaf. The lines on one side, describing an imagined scene in a Greek gymnasium, are not identifiably related to any of Whitman's published works. Those on the other side were used in the poem ultimately titled Song of Myself. which was first published in Leaves of Grass ( 1855 ).
- The Van Velsors, 1873; yal.00334; xxx.00589; prose 1 leaf handwritten printed (Box 3, Folder 125)
  Notes on the women of the Van Velsor family. Portions of this manuscript contributed to Some Personal and Old-Age Jottings, Good-Bye My Fancy ( 1891 ).
- [in Poetry of the Future], 1865–1875; yal.00076; xxx.00529; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 3, Fodler 113)
  A partial draft of Poetry of the Future, first published in North American Review 132 ( February 1881 ), 195–210. Whitman revised this essay and reprinted it as Poetry To-day in America—Shakespere—the Future in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–83 ).
- [other than merely literary points], 1876; yal.00117; xxx.00528; xxx.00537; xxx.00805; prose 2 leaves handwritten (Box 1, Folder 8)
  A heavily revised draft fragment, composed of several scraps of paper pasted together to form two leaves. The notes found on the first leaf were used in Preface, 1876, to the two-volume Centennial Edition of L. of G. and 'Two Rivulets' ( 1876 ). The prose fragment on the second leaf contributed to Darwinism—(then Furthermore), a short prose piece that orginally appeared in Two Rivulets ( 1876 ), but that was later incorporated into the Notes Left Over section of Collect in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–83 ). Both of these pieces were eventually included in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). Cancelled Civil War "reminiscences" on the Battle of First Fredericksburgh and the sinking of the U.S.S. Hatteras appear on the verso of the second leaf. Whitman wrote about both of these events in 'Tis But Ten Years Since (Third Paper), New York Weekly Graphic ( 14 February 1874 ).
- Walt Whitman's Last—Good-Bye My Fancy, 1891; yal.00146; xxx.00866; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 52)
  A draft of Walt Whitman's Last, which appeared in Lippincott's Magazine ( August 1891 ). On the verso of this manuscript is an incoming letter from F. A. Hilliard, dated 25 May 1891.
- An old man's rejoinder, 1890; yal.00318; xxx.00558; prose 9 leaves handwritten printed (Box 3, Folder 112)
  This manuscript is a draft of An Old Man's Rejoinder, first published in the Critic 17 ( 16 August 1890 ) before being reprinted in Good-Bye My Fancy ( 1891 ). Some of the versos include envelopes and letters to Whitman from A. Edward Newton, Charles A. Burkhardt, Charles B. Campbell.
- Copy of the OConnor preface, 1890; yal.00322; xxx.00586; prose 16 leaves handwritten (Box 3, Folder 115)
  A copy of Whitman's Preface to a volume of essays and tales by Wm. JD. O'Connor, pub'd posthumously in 1891, which appeared in Good-Bye My Fancy ( 1891 ), and in William Douglas O'Connor's Three Tales ( 1892 ).
- Preface, 1890; yal.00323; xxx.00586; prose 1 leaf handwritten printed (Box 3, Folder 115)
  A corrected galley proof of Whitman's Preface to William Douglas O'Connor's Three Tales ( 1892 ). Whitman included this preface in Good-Bye My Fancy ( 1891 ) as Preface to a volume of essays and tales by Wm. JD. O'Connor, pub'd posthumously in 1891.
- Walt Whitman's poem to-day at Dartmouth College, 1872; yal.00327; xxx.00867; xxx.00267; prose poetry 7 leaves handwritten printed (Box 3, Folder 118)
  A draft of Walt Whitman's Poem Today at Dartmouth College, an essay announcing the commencement poem Whitman delivered at Dartmouth June 26, 1872. This piece was published in the 26 June 1872 issue of the Washington Evening Star and includes excerpts from Whitman's poem, Thou Mother with Thy Equal Brood, originally published in the New York Herald 26 June 1872 under the title As a Strong Bird on Pinions Free. This poem was later published with seven other poems in a pamphlet, As a Strong Bird on Pinions Free ( 1872 ). It was also included in a supplement bound with Two Rivulets ( 1876 ). Whitman eventually changed the title to Thou Mother with Thy Equal Brood, added a new opening stanza, made additional revisions, and incorporated the poem into Leaves of Grass ( 1881–82 ).
- Convalescent hours, 1877; yal.00331; xxx.00826; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 3, Folder 122)
  This manuscript is a draft of the first paragraph of A Sun-Bath—Nakedness, published in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882 ).
- At the Complimentary Dinner, Camden, 1889; yal.00338; xxx.00579; prose 1 leaf handwritten printed (Box 3, Folder 129)
  A corrected proof of To Be Present Only, Whitman's response to an invitation to give an address at the complimentary dinner held in honor of his 70th birthday in Camden on 31 May 1889. Horace Traubel published Whitman's response as At the Complimentary Dinner, Camden, New Jersey, May 31, 1889 in Camden's Compliment to Walt Whitman, May 31, 1889: Notes, Addresses, Letters, Telegrams (Philadelphia: David McKay, 1889 ). Whitman later collected this response in Complete Prose ( 1892 ), under the title To Be Present Only.
- At the Complimentary Dinner, Camden, 1889; yal.00454; xxx.00579; prose 1 leaf handwritten printed (Box 3, Folder 129)
  A corrected proof of To Be Present Only, Whitman's response to an invitation to give an address at the complimentary dinner held in honor of his 70th birthday in Camden on 31 May 1889. Horace Traubel published Whitman's response as At the Complimentary Dinner, Camden, New Jersey, May 31, 1889 in Camden's Compliment to Walt Whitman, May 31, 1889: Notes, Addresses, Letters, Telegrams (Philadelphia: David McKay, 1889). Whitman later collected this response in Complete Prose ( 1892 ), under the title To Be Present Only.
- At the Complimentary Dinner, Camden, 1889; yal.00455; xxx.00579; prose 1 leaf handwritten printed (Box 3, Folder 129)
- Italian Music in Dakota, about 1881; yal.00080; xxx.00257; poetry 1 leaf handwritten printed (Box 3, Folder 153)
  Corrected galley proof of the poem Italian Music in Dakota, first published in Leaves of Grass ( 1881–82 ).
- Written Impromptu in an album, 1883; yal.00343; xxx.00483; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 3, Folder 139)
  Notes, dated 26 December 1883, which Whitman wrote to commemorate "these merry Christmas days and nights." The contents of this manuscript were used in Complete Prose ( 1892 ), under the title Written Impromptu in an Album.
- Walt Whitman's Last, 1891; yal.00353; xxx.00866; prose 1 leaf handwritten printed (Box 3, Folder 167)
  A corrected proof of Walt Whitman's Last, a short treatise on the theory behind Leaves of Grass, which includes a plug for Whitman's latest work, Good-Bye My Fancy. This piece of prose appeared in the August 1891 issue of Lippincott's Magazine.
- Whitman, Walt, poet, was born May 31, 1888; yal.00382; xxx.00589; xxx.00874; prose 2 leaves handwritten (Box 10, Folder 222)
  Draft notes towards an autobiographical essay. Portions of this manuscript were used in Autobiographic Note. From an old 'remembrance copy,' in Camden's Compliment to Walt Whitman, May 31, 1889: Notes, Addresses, Letters, Telegrams (Philadelphia: David McKay, 1889 ). Portions of this manuscript also appeared in Some Personal and Old-Age Jottings, first published in Good-Bye My Fancy ( 1891 ).
- I think the principal obstacle, 1882; yal.00422; xxx.00530; prose 1 leaf handwritten printed (Box 3, Folder 140)
  Whitman's notes on the "treatment of sex" as the chief obstacle to the advancement of women's rights, pasted to a backing sheet with a clipping of What Women Can Do from the New York Herald 17 April 1882. Portions of this manuscript were revised and used in A Memorandum at a Venture, first published in the June 1882 issue of the North American Review. This essay was reprinted in Specimen Days ( 1882 ).
- Silence, 1850–1865; yal.00441; xxx.00430; prose poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 3, Folder 140)
  Two manuscript scraps, pasted together to make one leaf. The top scrap is written in a looser hand, perhaps that of the 1860 s. The bottom scrap is composed in a neat and small hand, perhaps of the 1850 s. These two scraps are largely unrelated, perhaps the only connection between the two being the theme of silence. The relationship of the first scrap to Whitman's published work is unclear. However, portions of the second scrap are related to Great Are the Myths, first published, untitled, in the 1855 edition of Leaves of Grass as the concluding poem, and again in the 1856 edition as Poem of a Few Greatnesses. The poem went through many revisions through the different editions of Leaves of Grass, then was permanently dropped in 1881, except the two couplets that became the poem Youth, Day, Old Age, and Night. On the verso of this manuscript is the cancelled prose note: "do nothing but lose from the spread of slavery;—can get nothing but gain from the spread of free institutions.—"
- How often since that dark and chilly Saturday, 1880–1882; yal.00339; xxx.00531; prose 3 leaves handwritten (Box 3, Folder 130)
  A late draft of Death of Abraham Lincoln. Lecture deliver'd in New York, April 14, 1879 —in Philadelphia, ' 80 —in Boston, ' 81, published in Specimen Days ( 1882 ). Though Whitman delivered this lecture for the first time in April 1879, based on the letters which comprise the versos of this manuscript, this draft was not composed until some time after March 1880.